Nancy Pedrick Smith Mairs papers, 1937-2001 (bulk 1960-1995)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Nancy Pedrick Smith Mairs papers, 1937-2001 (bulk 1960-1995)
MS 381
Nancy Pedrick Smith Mairs,; Sally Jean Smith Caroline
Papers of author and poet Nancy Smith Mairs. Contains personal and family correspondence; family papers; photographs; educational, business, and professional papers; literary manuscripts, reviews, and collected writings.
10 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Author, poet, scholar, professor and self-described as a "non political feminist," Nancy Pedrick Smith Mairs, Ph.D. is well known for her autobiographical texts that speak about her life and her struggles with the debilitating disease, Multiple Sclerosis. Born July 23, 1943, in Long Beach, California, Mairs received an A.B. in English Literature from Wheaton College, an MFA in Creative Writing and a Ph.D. in English from the University of Arizona. She has taught writing on the high school and university level. Nancy Mairs is the author of nine books and countless newspaper and magazine articles. She has been the recipient of numerous awards including the Western States Book Award in 1984 for In All the Rooms of the Yellow House. Her writings have been regularly reviewed in the New York Times and on National Public Radio. Ms. Mairs currently lives in Tucson, AZ with her husband of thirty-nine years, George Mairs.
Organization
This collection is organized into 4 Series.
Series 1: Family Papers and Photographs, 1937-1993
Series 2: Education, 1952-1984
Series 3: Professional Life and Career, 1970-2001
Series 4: Publications and Writings, 1946-2001
Scope and Content Note
Series 1: Family Papers and Photographs-Correspondence sections are arranged alphabetically by major correspondent with incoming and outgoing designation.
Series 2: Education materials are arranged chronologically.
Series 3: Professional Life and Career is arranged chronologically within the section on Nancy Mairs teaching career and alphabetically concerning her literary career.
Series 4: Publications and Writings are arranged alphabetically.
Access Terms
Mairs, Nancy, 1943- -- Archives
Mairs, Nancy, 1943- -- Correspondence
Feminists -- United States -- Archives
Multiple sclerosis -- Patients
Container List
- Series 1: Family Papers and Photographs, 1937-1993
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence: Nancy Smith Mairs, 1952 -
    - Incoming--Browning, Druke & Hawkins-Attorneys at Law- Druke, Carole Wilson. March 4, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-Byrne Viral International Clinic. 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Clementine, Michel. May 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Collins, Kristina. February 1961 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-Comey, David. 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Cutler, Anne Pedrick Smith. February 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Dwyer, Carol August. 1960 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Gloster, Alice and Winston, Roni. May 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Kefferstan, Jean Pedrick. ca. 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Kefferstan, Jean Pedrick. 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. 1961 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. 1961 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. 1962 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. 1962 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. January 1963 - May 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. July 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. September 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. October 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Mairs George Anthony. November 1963 - December 1963 (Box 1)
    - Incoming-Mairs, Nancy Smith. (Box 1)
    - Incoming-- Moffett David Lloyd 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - Incoming-- Moffett David Lloyd. April 1962 - December 1962 (Box 2)
    - Incoming-- Padmore George Arthur. January 1960 - February 1960 (Box 2)
    - Incoming-- Padmore George Arthur. December 1960 (Box 2)
    - Incoming-"Roz." April 19, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Incoming-- Smith Sally Jean. ca. 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Incoming-- Ure Marguerite Louisa ("Poo"). August 1960 - September 1960 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing--Christmas letters. 1981-1989 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-- Cutler Nathan and Cutler Anne Pedrick Smith. January 1963 - August 1963 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-Cutler, Anne and Nathan. 1973-1976 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-Cutler, Anne and Nathan. 1977 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-Cutler, Anne and Nathan. 1978 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-Cutler, Anne and Nathan. 1979 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-- Kefferstan Jean Pedrick. October 1960 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-- Kefferstan Jean Pedrick. July 1963 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-Letters-to-the-editor. 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-- Mairs George Anthony. February 1961 - May 1961 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing-- Mairs George Anthony. January 1962 - July 1962 (Box 2)
    - 3 Outgoing-- Mairs George Anthony. August 1962 - October 1962 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing-- Mairs George Anthony. November 1962 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing-- Mairs George Anthony. January 1963 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing-- Smith John E. Sr. and Smith Ann Louise Sawyer. 1952 - 1958 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing-- "Tooth Fairy " ca. 1948-1950 (Box 3)
  - Subseries 2: Correspondence: George Anthony Mairs, 1953-
    - Episcopal Church-- Christ Church Parish, Waltham, Massachusetts-- Confirmation Certificate. May 1953 (Box 3)
  - Subseries 3: Correspondence: Anne Pedrick Smith, 1937-1947
    - Incoming-- Davis, Charles. October 1937 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Friend, Norma A May. 1942 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Pedrick, Elfrieda V. August 1942-1943 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, Ann Louise Sawyer. April 1942 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. October 1937-December 1937 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. January 1938 - May 1938 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. June 1938 - December 1938 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. January 1939 - December 1939 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. January 1940-February 1940 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. March 1940 - June 1940 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. September 1940-October 1940 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. November1940-December 1940 (Box 3)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. January 1941-February 1941 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. March 1941-April 1941 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. May 1941 - December 1941 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. February 1942 - November 1942 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. May 1943 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. June 1943 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. July 1943 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. August 1943 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. September 1943 - October 1943 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. November 1943 (Box 4)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. December 1943 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. January 1944 - May 1944 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. January 1945 - April 1945 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. February 1946 - March 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. April 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. June 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. July 1, 1946 - July 14, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. July 15, 1946-July 30, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. August 1, 1946 - August 15, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. August 16, 1946 - August 31, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. September 1, 1946 - September 14, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. September 15, 1946 - September 30, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. October 1, 1946 - October 12, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. October 13, 1946 - October 31, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. November 1946 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, John E Jr. October 1947 (Box 5)
    - Incoming-- Smith, Sallie, April 1942 (Box 5)
    - Outgoing-- Pedrick, Elfrieda V. March 1943-April 1943 (Box 5)
    - Outgoing-- Pedrick, Elfrieda V. May 1943 (Box 5)
    - Outgoing-- Pedrick, Elfrieda V. June 1943 (Box 5)
    - Outgoing-- Pedrick, Elfrieda V. July 1943 (Box 5)
    - Outgoing-- Pedrick, Elfrieda V. September 1943-December 1943 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing-Pedrick, Elfrieda V. September 1944 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing-Pedrick, Elfrieda V. July 1947 - August 1947 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing-Smith, John E Jr. March 1942 - May 1942 (Box 6)
  - Subseries 4: Correspondence: John E. Smith Jr. 1938-1947
    - Award-- Rennselaer Polytechnic Institute Society of the Sigma Xi. 1946 (Box 6)
    - Incoming-- Burrell G.S. (Captain U.S. Navy). March 1946 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing-- Smith John E. Sr. and Smith, Ann Louise Sawyer. July 1938 - August 1938 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing-- Smith John E. Sr. and Smith, Ann Louise Sawyer. October 1938 - November 1938 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing-- Smith John E. Sr. and Smith, Ann Louise Sawyer. May 1943 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing-- Smith John E. Sr. and Smith, Ann Louise Sawyer. June 1947 - August 1955 (Box 6)
  - Subseries 5: Correspondence: Jean Pedrick Kefferstan.
    - Poetry. (Box 6)
  - Subseries 6: Personal items, Photographs, media items. 1957-1992
    - Personal items-Nancy and George Mairs-biographical information, news articles, marriage items, zodiac chart, and children's writings. 1962-1985 (Box 6)
    - Society of Mayflower Descendants-certificate. January 18, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Photographs-Nancy Smith Mairs. (Box 6)
    - Photographs-Vineyard Sailing Camp-album. 1957-1958 (Box 6)
    - Media-Audio tapes (2); reel to reel (2); arm bracelet-Mairs 1992, no date (Box 6)
- Series 2: Education, 1952-1984
  - Subseries 1: K-12. 1952-1960
    - Exeter Day School-Bugle-poem by Nancy Smith The Wind-4th grade. (Box 7)
    - Wenham School Department Weekday Church School. 1952-1953, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
    - Peabody Institute-concert. June 22, 1955 (Box 7)
    - Beverly High School-The AEGIS-publication. Winter 1958-1959; Spring and Fall 1959, Winter 1960 (Box 7)
    - Beverly High School-English-writings. 1957-1960 (Box 7)
    - Beverly High School-diploma. June 16, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Subseries 2: Wheaton College (Undergraduate degree). 1960-1964
    - 7 Correspondence. 1960 (Box 7)
    - Awards. 1961-1963 (Box 7)
    - Bachelor of Arts-degree. June 17, 1964 (Box 7)
    - English 131. 1960-1961 (Box 7)
    - English 303. Fall 1961-Spring 1962 (Box 7)
    - English 342a. Fall 1962-Spring 1963 (Box 7)
    - English 304. Spring 1963 (Box 7)
    - English 392b. Spring 1963 (Box 7)
    - English 305. Fall 1963-Spring 1964 (Box 7)
    - English. 1964 (Box 7)
    - The Wheaton College Alumnae Magazine-article by Jean Pedrick-Nancy Mairs' aunt ( Wolf Moon). August 1974 (Box 7)
    - The Wheaton College Alumnae Magazine-article ( For Better, For Verse) and poetry-pages 7-9 (2 copies). Winter 1974 (Box 7)
    - Honorary degree-correspondence. 1993 (Box 7)
    - Wheaton Quarterly-article. Summer 1994 (Box 7)
  - Subseries 3: University of Arizona (Graduate degree). 1972-1975
    - English 325. Fall 1972 (Box 7)
    - English 299. Summer 1973 (Box 7)
    - English 326/poetry reading. Fall 1973 (Box 7)
    - English 399a. Spring 1974 (Box 7)
    - English Spring. 1974 (Box 7)
    - MFA Writing Project-Fright (2 copies). 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - Masters of Fine Arts-degree. September 1, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Subseries 4: University of Arizona (Ph.D. degree). 1977-1984
    - Correspondence-references. 1978-1981 (Box 7)
    - English 396. Fall 1977 (Box 7)
    - English 396i. Fall 1977 (Box 7)
    - English 596g. Spring 1980 (Box 7)
    - English Fall. 1981 (Box 7)
    - Literary Criticisms. Fall 1981 (Box 7)
    - English 515b. Spring 1982 (Box 7)
    - English 557b. Spring 1982 (Box 7)
    - English 596e. Spring 1983 (Box 7)
    - Preliminary Doctoral Examinations-Other Love-Literary Essays and Reviews. ca.1983 (Box 7)
    - Other Love-Literary Essays and Reviews-Voice Lessons. ca. 1983 (Box 7)
    - Other Love-Literary Essays and Reviews-Body at Work. ca.1983 (Box 7)
    - Other Love-Literary Essays and Reviews-Notes from the Field. ca.1983 (Box 7)
    - 8 Preliminary Doctoral Exams. January 4, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Preliminary Doctoral Exams. April 1983 (Box 8)
    - Dissertation proposal. May 1984 (Box 8)
    - Dissertation proposal-Plaintext. 1984 (Box 8)
    - Dissertation-Plaintext. 1984 (Box 8)
    - Doctor of Philosophy-degree. December 21, 1984 (Box 8)
- Series 3: Professional Life and Career, 1970-2001
  - Subseries 1: Teaching, 1978-1986
    - English 596e. Fall 1979 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - English 210. Spring 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - English 304. Spring 1982 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - English 308. Fall 1982 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence-references. 1983 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - English 207. Fall 1983 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - English 101. Fall 1985 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - English 102. Spring 1986 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Arizona English Bulletin. February 1978, February 1980, October 1981, Winter 1985 (Box 8)
  - Subseries 2: Business Correspondence, 1970-2001
    - Beacon Press. 1991-1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Confluence Press-Certificate of Copyright- In All the Rooms of the Yellow House. 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Fan Mail 1978-1987 (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
    - Harper Row Publishers 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - National Writers Union Wayne State University. 1999, Judith Siegel Pearson Committee. 1986 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Misc-publishers. 1970 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous. July 2000-March 2001 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 3: Awards, Certificates, Conferences, Grant, 1980-1997
    - Awards-correspondence. 1980, 1983, 1989, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Awards-Bread Loaf Writers'. 1982, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Awards-Western States Art Foundation. 1984 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Awards-Ohio Spring Literary Festival. 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 21.)
    - Certificate-Tucson/Pima Arts Council. 1993 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Santa Cruz Writers's conference. 1980, Women's Review Conference.; National Leadership Conference. 1988 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Grant: National Endowment for the Arts. 1991 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Series 4: Publications and Writings, 1946-2001
  - Subseries 1: Publications and published writings 1972-2001
    - Instead It Is Winter -The Maguey Press-publication. 1977 (Box 8)
    - The Academy of American Poets-Selections: University & College Poetry Prizes. 1973-1978 (Box 8)
    - The American Voice. Summer 1988 (Box 8)
    - ANIMA. Fall 1982 (2 copies), Fall 1983, Spring 1988 (Box 8)
    - Arion's Dolphin: A Quarterly of Poetry. Spring 1972; Spring 1973 (Box 9)
    - Cambridge Street Artists Cooperative (Ms. Mairs first public reading) (3 copies). 1972 (Box 9)
    - The Christian Century. November 21-28 2001 (Box 9)
    - Contemporary American Poetry. -bibliography. May 1987 (Box 9)
    - Greenhouse Review. 1977 (Box 9)
    - Kaleidoscope-International Magazine of Literature, Fine Arts, and Disability. Summer/Fall 1986 (Box 9)
    - The Little Magazine. Spring 1972 (Box 9)
    - The Louisville Review. Spring 1977 (Box 9)
    - New Poets: Women-an anthology. 1976 (Box 9)
    - New York Times-Hers column. July-August 1987 (Box 9)
    - New York Times Book Review: When Bad Things Happen to Good Writers. February 21, 1993 (Box 9)
    - Prickly Pear/Tucson-Poetry. Quarterly Spring 1984 (Box 9)
    - Room of One's Own Vol. 7 #4. 1982 (Box 9)
    - Transforming Fire: Women Using Anger Creatively. 1999 (Box 9)
    - Women's Review of Books: Conspiracies of Silence-article. July 1989 (Box 9)
    - Writing Nature: An Ecological Reader for Writers. 1995 (Box 9)
    - You Gotta Suit Up For 'Em All-Magazine's Datebook. 1979 (Box 9)
    - Book Reviews by Nancy Smith Mairs. 1985-1996 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous articles 1986-1995 (Box 9)
  - Subseries 2: Writings/Publicity/Reviews, 1946-2000
    - Beast of my Heart-draft. (Box 9)
    - Bibliography of Feminist Literary Theory and Scholarship. (Box 9)
    - Body at Work-Part 1 and 2. (Box 9)
    - Brush. (Box 9)
    - Carnal Acts-Uncorrected Proof. 1990 (Box 9)
    - Carnal Acts-Running Head Copy. 1990 (Box 9)
    - Carnal Acts: A Prose Miscellany. 1990 (Box 9)
    - Carnal Acts-Publicity and Reviews. 1990-1996 (Box 9)
    - Challenge. (Box 10)
    - Desserts. November 13, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Fiction-miscellaneous odds and ends. 1981 (Box 10)
    - Garrett in Grey (A Bad Business). (Box 10)
    - Glamour magazine-correspondence and draft of article- Young and Disabled-unpublished. 1995 (Box 10)
    - Helix (2 copies). (Box 10)
    - House Bound. 1987 (Box 10)
    - Houses. (Box 10)
    - In All the Rooms of the Yellow House. ca. 1984 (Box 10)
    - In the Weald of Kent Summer. 1994 (Box 10)
    - Writing about taxes and money. ca. 1998-1999 (Box 10)
    - Journal. 1973 (Box 10)
    - Journal-Intensive. 1977-1980 (Box 10)
    - Journal. 1986-1992 (Box 10)
    - A Letter to Matthew. July 1983 (Box 10)
    - Linguistics of Dress. (Box 10)
    - The Little Locksmith by Katherine Butler Hathaway-correspondence. 1999-2000 (Box 10)
    - The Little Locksmith by Katherine Butler Hathaway-copy. 1991 (Box 10)
    - The Journals and Letters of The Little Locksmith by Katherine Butler Hathaway - copy. 1946 (Box 10)
    - Making Ready. (Box 10)
    - Midsummer: The Farm. (Box 10)
    - Non-fiction-odds and ends. ca. 1990 (Box 10)
    - On Being a Cripple. August 1982 (Box 10)
    - On Being a Scientific Booby. December 1981 (Box 10)
    - On Raising a Daughter. July 1982 (Box 10)
    - On Woman Writing-correspondence and reviews. 1986 (Box 10)
    - On Woman Writing. June 1984 (Box 10, Folder [3 folders])
    - Ordinary Times. 1993 (Box 10, Folder [5 folders])
    - Reviews and Publicity- Ordinary Times. 1993-1995 (Box 10, Folder [2 folders])
    - Outside Feast and Fast. (Box 11, Folder [2 folders])
    - Plaintext-Uncorrected Proofs. April 4, 1986 (Box 11)
    - Plaintext -Introduction. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext-On Having Adventures. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext- On Touching by Accident. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext- Woman with Full Red Lips. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext-Ron Her Son. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext- On Not Liking Sex. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext- On Keeping Women Out. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext- On Loving Men. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext- On Living Behind Bars. (Box 11)
    - Plaintext-Reviews and Publicity. 1986 (Box 11)
    - Plaintext-Reviews and Publicity. 1986-1988 (Box 11)
    - Plaintext-Publicity. 1992-1995 (Box 11)
    - Poetry- For Anne in Sleep-unpublished. 1986 (Box 11)
    - Poetry-odds and ends. (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House-1st manuscript. (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House. 1989 (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House-pgs. 2-207. 1989 (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House-pgs 208-454. 1989 (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House-Preface, and The Way In. (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House-The Way In. (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House-The Port. (Box 11, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-In Exeter. (Box 11, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-Elsewhere. (Box 11, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-236. (Box 11, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-Sorties. (Box 11)
    - Remembering the Bone House-Lost in Space. (Box 11, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-The Farm. (Box 11, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-Inside and Outside. (Box 12, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-The Desert. (Box 12, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-Here at Home. (Box 12, Folder [2 folders])
    - Remembering the Bone House-Reviews and Publicity. 1989-1995 (Box 12)
    - Shape. (Box 12)
    - A Troubled Guest: Life and Death Stories-Pgs. 1-108. (Box 12)
    - A Troubled Guest: Life and Death Stories-Pgs. 109-246. (Box 12)
    - A Troubled Guest: Life and Death Stories-Reviews and publicity. 2001 (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-prelude. 1995 (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-Parts 1 and 2. (Box 12, Folder [2 folders])
    - Voice Lessons-Pear Trees-Groves of Academe. (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-Body at Work. (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-Reading Others. (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-In Search of "In Search of Our Mothers' Gardens": Alice Walker. (Box 12, Folder [2 folders])
    - Voice Lessons-Reading Houses, Writing Lives. (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-Notes from the Field. (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-Notes and Works Cited. (Box 12)
    - Voice Lessons-Book Reviews. 1994 (Box 12)
    - Waist High in the World-Correspondence. 1994-1995 (Box 12)
    - Waist High in the World-manuscript. (Box 12)
    - Waist High in the World-The Wider World. (Box 12)
    - Waist High in the World-Home Truths. (Box 12)
    - Waist High in the World-misc. (Box 12)
    - Waist High in the World-Reviews and Publicity. 1996-1998 (Box 12)
    - The Writer's Thin Skin and Faint Heart. (Box 12)
    - Writing into Life-Parts 1 and 2. (Box 12)
    - No title. March 7, 1979 (Box 12)
    - Writings-Miscellaneous. (Box 12, Folder [2 folders])
  - Subseries 3: Readings/Speaking engagements/Collected Writings, 1984-2001
    - Readings/Speaking engagements. 1998-2001 (Box 12)
    - Readings-misc. (Box 12)
    - Interviews with Nancy Mairs-articles. 1986-1995 (Box 12)
    - Collected published writings-miscellaneous reviews and publicity. 1984 (Box 12)
    - Collected published writings-miscellaneous reviews and publicity. 1988-1995 (Box 12)
  - Subseries 4: Oversized Items, 1967-2002
    - Brentwoods 225 Years -pg 43 paragraph on the Kefferstan home-Nancy Mairs's aunt Jean Pedrick Kefferstan. 1967 (Box 13)
    - Glamour magazine. November 1994 (Box 13)
    - Collected writings-Chithra Radha Perumalswami- Writing from "Waist-High": Nancy Mairs's Autobiographical Essays and the Subject of Disability - B.A. Thesis. Spring 2000 (Box 13)
    - Women's Foundation of Southern Arizona: In Celebration of Women-program. 2002 (Box 13)
    - Damaged Hard Drive - in box. (Box 13)
    - Floppy disks of Mairs writing. (Box 13)
    - Beta tape. (Box 13)
    - 1984 Western States Book Award-autographed by the 4 recipients including Ms. Mairs. (Box 13, Othertype poster)
    - Instead It Is Winter -publication. 1977 (Box 14)